<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: flow | Scattered Thoughts]]></title>
  <link href="http://scattered-thoughts.net/blog/categories/flow/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://scattered-thoughts.net/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-25T23:23:46-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://scattered-thoughts.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jamie Brandon]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[jamie@scattered-thoughts.net]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[External memory]]></title>
    <link href="http://scattered-thoughts.net/blog/2013/05/21/flowing-faster-external-memory/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-21T20:43:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://scattered-thoughts.net/blog/2013/05/21/flowing-faster-external-memory</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p> What work I do that is worthwhile happens in the few hours of flow I manage to achieve every week. A million different things break that flow every day. I suspect that a large part of achieving flow is keeping the current problem in working memory. To improve my chances I can improve my working memory, offload parts of the problem to the computer or prevent context switches. I&rsquo;m on my own with the first option, but a better development environment can help with the latter two.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>The first thing that I want to fix in this series is offloading memory. There are basically two kinds of questions I regularly deal with:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>How did I solve this problem / build this software / configure this program X months ago?</p></li>
<li><p>What was I trying to remember to change X seconds ago?</p></li>
</ul>


<p>I&rsquo;ve started using <a href="http://jblevins.org/projects/deft/">deft</a> to answer both of these. Deft stores notes in a folder full of flat files and adds an incremental search buffer to emacs (searching > organising). This means that my notes are simple plain text which I can easily edit, backup, grep or serve on the web.</p>

<p>For long-term memory I create a new note every time I solve a problem or learn something useful. Within emacs M-&lsquo; brings up the deft window, typing triggers the incremental search and hiting Enter opens the first matching note.</p>

<p>For short-term memory I have a single note called stack. Hitting C-&lsquo; opens the stack note with the cursor on a new blank line for adding items to the stack. Hitting C-DEL deletes the previous line and C-q closes the stack. Hopefully this is sufficiently low-friction that the extra memory makes up for the context switch.</p>

<p>My config is <a href="https://github.com/jamii/emacs-live-packs/blob/master/deft-pack/init.el">here</a>. I&rsquo;m considering writing a gnome-shell extension which displays the last line of the stack in the status bar to remind me what I&rsquo;m supposed to be doing when my mental stack gets rudely dumped. I also want to add the global key bindings to gnome-shell so I don&rsquo;t have to navigate to emacs first.</p>

<p>This is a very simple tool, which is kind of the point. The more stucture and options added to a note-taking tool the more effort it takes to actually use it and the more likely it is that I lose my entire mental stack whilst doing so.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
